JLM: Speaking of Syria, let me point out that Al Qaeda
is apparently the ally of allies - because apparently, that's the way they are referred to -
that is, François Hollande, Mr Obama and others.
So Al Qaeda is their ally under the name of Al Nusra, but we fight them in Afghanistan.
They're bad guys in Afghanistan, but they're good guys in Syria,
and ISIS are the bad guys in Syria, but the good guys when they fight the Kurds.
This situation is confused, and people are being put on. So what's going on there?
All the great powers are involved in this situation, as well as the main financiers in the region, that is, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and Iran.
This war is a very classic and conventional war that aims at destroying countries
that have always been a problem to the Gulf monarchies, Turkey and Iran.
The strategy of France and the USA is clearly a flop,
because ISIS, that was supposed to be contained in one place, is now somewhere else.
Let me remind you that the last time we fought them, it was in Iraq, but they're now in Syria,
although we were supposed to have attacked them on countless occasions.
These people have a curious capacity to resist bombings,
and now, they're in Syria, and we're putting on the same act again, and it doesn't have any effect.
The Russians are there too now to strike ISIS - and they're doing quite well -, and barely did they arrive
that they were criticized for bombing opponents and civilians.
Journalist: That's what an NGO said.
JLM: Do we have to believe it just because it's an NGO? Journalist: Well, why not?
JLM: Why not, you're right? But why would you not believe me?
Believe me, my information about the situation is at least as good as that of this NGO.
What should we say? That they bomb civilians? Of course they do!
Have you ever seen a war in which civilians are not killed by bombings? It doesn't exist!
The bombings by the well-intentioned belligerants in Yemen prove it.
As you know, these belligerants did good to the 40,000 people they killed.
Well they bomb weddings. In Afghanistan, we bomb hospitals.
But not in Yemen, because they're the "good guys", so we don't talk about it. We'll talk about those who... (inaudible)
Journalist: According to the NGO you disagree with, Russia mainly bombs the rebels we praised 4 years ago when they rose against the regime.
JLM: Well I did not. I never praised them, so I don't see why...
Journalist: Don't you think there's such a thing as moderate opposition to Bashar Al Assad?
JLM: Of course not! Have you ever seen moderate Islamists except in your newspapers? It doesn't exist! On the field they're as savage as the rest!
Journalist: No, no! Many western leaders say there is a moderate opposition.
JLM: Yeah, yeah, depending on their whims! I just told you that the moderates were Al Qaeda,
although we said they were terrorists less than two months ago, and we are bombing them in Afghanistan. This is a joke!
Why am I so passionate about this issue? After all, I could wash my hands of it!
But this war could spread to the rest of the world, there's a risk of a global war!
The British speak of bombing the Russian planes that supposedly violate an airspace. This is crazy!
We should not do that! We should come to the table and talk with those who are involved in the war.
Journalist: Does this also include Bashar Al Assad?
Other journalist: Bashar Al Assad, who is responsible for slaughtering his people, I just say it in passing...
JLM: Yes of course! We are now going to repeat this in unison with the people behind the camera...
Journalist: It's a fact...
JLM: But the question you should ask me is "Should we negotiate with ISIS?" It doesn't seem to bother you.
I just said we should negotiate with those who are involved in the war, and the first person you think of is Bashar Al Assad.
So to you, ISIS is not the enemy.
To you all, our main enemy is Bashar Al Assad, and you don't even know why.
You think our main objective is to bring down Al Assad's government, whatever the cost,
well I disagree with bringing down his regime at any cost.
I think he should go, and that there should be a national unity government.
But he should go only if the circumstances allow an honest agreement.
because otherwise, Syria will turn into a new version of Lybia. Is that what you want?
Journalist: We understood your point. JLM I hope you did...
The solution to this type of situation is rarely a military one, everyone knows this.
If that was the case, there would be joy and hapiness in Lybia, Iraq and Afghanistan.
In these countries, we defended "great, interesting and intelligent causes",
and it resulted in absolute chaos, atrocious sufferings
and the massive immigration of poor people who flee a situation that no one no longer controls.